By the wall, I will say a word to you.
Take my word.
Give ear to my instructions.
(Ancient Sumerian clay tablet)
2199 AD
I repeat, this is the 7th Cosmo Marine Regiment calling from the Moon.
We were attacked by enemy carrier-based fighters
and are stranded on the Moon.
Have taken heavy losses.
Requesting evac. Requesting evac.
Are you sure that thing is fixed?
It should be.
This is the 7th Cosmo Marine regiment calling from the Moon.
We were attacked by enemy carrier-based fighters
and are stranded on the Moon.
Colonel!
Have taken heavy losses.
Requesting evac. Requesting evac.
Is that you, Saito?
What a face to wake up to...
This is the 7th Cosmo Marine Regiment calling from the Moon.
We were attacked by enemy carrier-based fighter
and are stranded on the Moon.
Transmit all you want, it won't help.
Have taken heavy losses.
Kurata!
It's the truth.
Requesting evac.
The top brass have forgotten we even exist.
They'll come for us.
We don't give up as long as there's life left in us.
That's what it means to be a Cosmo Marine.
Never forget that!
Yes, sir!
What's that?
I've never seen a ship like that before.
It's not Gamilan, either.
Cosmo Navy, then?
Hey, look.
Colonel, there's a friendly out there!
Help has arrived!
Oh, no...
Kiryu!
We're about to leave lunar orbit.
Maintain heading.
All ahead half.
All ahead half, aye!
Hey, what do you think you're doing?!
No unauthorized personnel on the bridge!
Move it! I have something to say!
Oh, dear...
You're this boat's captain?
If you'd shown up sooner, my regiment wouldn't have been wiped out!
You were getting our mayday, right?
Why did you wait so‒
I'm the captain.
Then who‒
Commander, UN Cosmo Force Space Defense Command.
Admiral Hijikata.
To defeat the Gamilans and restore our home to her blue state.
We were deployed to provide escort
for a special ship that's been tasked with that mission.
So you're saying that rescuing us was just an afterthought, sir?!
Yes.
That ship we saw?
What the hell was that?
We fought and died for this, too! We have a right to know!
Hey, now...
That was the Yamato.
Yamato?
That's right, the Yamato.
The space battleship Yamato.
Helmed by my best friend.
And also...
...the last hope of the human race.
Odyssey of the Celestial Ark
I am Melda Ditz, 707th Air Wing, Milky Way Theater Forces.
If you ever lose a close family member in this war, you'll understand.
We can trust each other. That's what my gut tells me.
These Gatlanteans are nothing to fear!
Calm yourself, Berger.
The more cunning the prey, the more satisfying the kill.
Those ruins were left behind by the race that built the gate.
Now I am all alone...
Open all gun ports! Shoot down the Yamato!
We are hereby abandoning the Yamato Project.
This has to end here!
Steady as she goes! All ahead, emergency speed!
If we don't take a gamble to snatch victory from the jaws of defeat,
we'll never break through this blockade!
This is the Okita Gambit...
Wave Motion Gun, fire!
Lay in course 728. Destination, the Rainbow Cluster! All ships, lift off!
Here's a present! Accept it with my compliments!
Yuki! Yuki!
So, Heaven is telling me to destroy the Yamato myself?
You think I'm going to let it end this way?!
Glory and blessings to Gamilas!
Your people repurposed wave motion energy as a weapon.
I shall make alterations to this ship.
And the Yamato herself will become integral
to the Cosmo Reverse System.
7 months since the Yamato set sail from Earth
Intergalactic space outside the Large Magellanic Cloud
Really?
It certainly seems to be.
Apparently, Baleras has fallen
and Chancellor Dessler has died in battle.
Fine news, indeed.
I'd thought that after failing to assassinate Dessler,
we would be doomed to wander the cosmos forever.
But if he has died and his regime has fallen...
Returning home is no longer a pipe dream.
What's that? Gravity tremors dead ahead?
Exactly.
Lt. General Bandevel!
What is it?
What was that?! What's going on?!
Multiple enemy vessels detected outside our firing range dead ahead!
Identifying ship types...
They're Gatlantean!
Filthy barbarians! Counterattack!
Fleet attrition rate, 95 barsel!
W-We're being wiped out?!
Wh-What is that?!
Barbarians have such technology?
No, it's not possible...
Wh-What do we do, sir?
Stay calm!
The Sehrgut's front armor can withstand anything!
Fire!
Go to full speed!
Hurry!
Have you learned your lesson,
you blue Gamilan vermin?
Personal log, Mikage Kiryu, Technical Division.
It's been a month since the Yamato set sail from Iscandar,
and the ship will soon leave the LMC's outer rim
and enter intergalactic space.
Comms Officer.
Shift change, sir.
Having received the Cosmo Reverse System,
morale aboard the ship is high.
Okay, Ichikawa.
Hold the fort.
I will.
What about you?
Saijo will relieve me.
Thanks to Starsha's mediation, the threat from Gamilas is behind us.
But over the course of our journey to Iscandar,
we've lost a great many shipmates.
But even as we sail on,
the people waiting back on Earth for the Yamato to return
are fighting against the fear of the extinction that looms ever closer.
We continue to carry out our daily duties.
For our families and loved ones waiting on Earth...
for our shipmates who fell with the mission still unfinished,
we'll do everything in our power.
That's all.
And as for me, my days are spent analyzing alien languages
with Lt. Niimi, my immediate superior.
If we can build a rudimentary translation device,
it should allow us to make friendly contact with aliens.
Signing off.
Incoming Call
Yes?
Do you know what time it is?
Oh, crap!
Dinner! Dinner! Dinner!
Oh, crap! Oh, crap! Oh, crap!
Dinner! Dinner!
Oh, crap! Oh, crap!
C'mon Shino, hurry up‒
Ow...
I wish I had free time like you.
Wha‒?
Oh, crap!
It would've been cuter if she'd been eating a piece of toast.
Kiryu Mikage.
Tech Division ace, personally scouted by Miss Niimi.
A linguist in the making.
You're full of facts, Nemo.
She's not cute!
Not one damn bit!
Was that really a good idea?
You're being paranoid.
Iscandar mediated an agreement with Gamilas.
Right?
I sure hope you're right...
Whatever happens, we'll have to make do
without the Wave Motion Gun now.
Dimensional Wave Motion Implosion Emitter
Emitter Aperture Plug
It's Kodai, sir. May I come in?
Shouldn't you be in bed, sir?
I feel good today.
What is it?
Nothing, sir. I'm not here on any business in particular.
That's an old tune.
It was originally a German folk song.
Thank you.
There's a version of this with Japanese lyrics.
It's about friends who part, hoping that they will be reunited.
Partings are difficult.
But people always meet again.
I had a reunion, too.
On Iscandar.
It turned out to be a final farewell, though.
Even if it was just a video,
I'm glad that I got to see him.
How he lived, how he cared for others,
and what his parting words would be...
I feel like I know now.
The first time I met Mamoru Kodai...
Yes, he must have been about the same age you are.
I wish he could have served aboard this ship with us.
Yes, sir.
It's the strangest thing.
I feel like he's still here with us.
So do I.
I'm interested in hearing that version
you mentioned with the Japanese lyrics.
Maybe I'll put in a request for it on Misaki's radio show, then.
I think that's a great idea.
House call!
We're coming in.
Hm?
Kodai?
Oh, you're here?
I'll be going, sir.
Kodai.
Stop by to visit again.
I will, sir.
You two are like father and son!
You think so?
Huh?
I've been thinking about my brother.
You were?
You've been doing the same thing as me, then.
While he was on Iscandar, your brother...
Say, Yamamoto...
Yes?
Having a sibling is a great thing, isn't it?
Yes.
Hey.
What're you hanging out here for?
Well, I'm off shift at the moment.
In that case...
Gamilan multi-language translator
Now to translate the Gatlantean into Jirellan...
Like a river, time flows, finding its way back to the distant depths.
I'm making good progress...
You're as fast as ever.
I've also installed it into my head
so I'll be able to use it in an emergency.
My assignment just came in a little while ago.
Get this, it's a huge coincidence!
Believe it or not, it's the same unit as you.
Meria, I went and survived again...
So we'll always be together.
Fomt, let's go see Koronarl at night with my sister‒
Message, sir!
Acting Captain Berger!
"Major" is fine.
Yes, sir.
Um, you're requested on the bridge.
Coming.
Inertial control's out?
Yeah. They say it's gonna take a while to get it back online.
I've brought him, sir!
Sorry to make you come here.
The ship's intercom is down.
She's showing her age, just like us.
Good work, boy.
Garle Dessler!
So, what is it, Pops?
We've received orders from the MP Fleet to come to a halt.
With the captain dead,
you're the ranking officer aboard the ship, Berger.
What are your orders? Do we stop?
We ignore them, obviously!
Are you sure?
The orders came from the Gelvades-class Mirangal.
The Mirangal?
Oh, right.
From her ship, huh?
Inertial control restored.
Repair crews, you may work with your magnetic shoes turned off.
I don't care what the top brass decided,
I can't do that after all they've done!
Any attacks against the Yamato are forbidden.
That's an order.
Who could obey an order like‒
Excuse me.
Anyway, I can't accept it.
Here, ma'am.
Thank you.
Pardon the interruption!
I want to destroy that thing, the Yamato, personally!
I want to make them pay for killing Gen. Domel and my friends!
I want revenge!
Still the same old foolish man, I see.
I was born that way.
So, how was he?
The Major was livid!
I don't doubt it.
The captain of the Mirangal was so pretty!
Little Miss Neredia, you mean?
"Little Miss"?
Your crew is nothing but old-timers and child soldiers.
Do you want to start playing war again
and get even little boys like that mixed up in it?
Yes, I do!
Reconcile with the Terrons?
Gen. Domel,
Getto, Kraitz, Old Man Heydeln!
They were all killed by those people!
Like when you got that?
In any case,
we should leave this sector as soon as possible.
A witch lives here.
Someone who entices sailors with her beautiful voice
and gobbles up their very souls? That kind?
Countless ships have vanished from these coordinates.
Countless.
What a load of garbage. Superstitious nonsense.
Bridge! Why are you playing a song over the intercom?!
Sir? No one is playing a song.
What do you call this singing, then?!
I don't hear any singing.
Fomt?
Occupied, huh?
Waiting for someone?
Uh... Hey.
Say cheese.
Did you get it?
Of course I did.
That was mean!
Don't be such a baby. It'll make memories.
And now, a shot of our two lovely ladies in their finery!
Yamamoto, let's get a shot together!
Okay, ladies! Say cheese!
Got 'em!
Who gave the order to fire?
I did, sir!
Where's the Commander?
He isn't on the bridge.
Whose ships are they? Gamilas?
I hailed them using standard Gamilan codes,
but there was no reply.
Radar returns!
Large vessels!
Count, 5!
Matching data.
It's the Terron Yamatte!
Attack squadron has struck the first spear!
Transmit visuals to Megaruda!
Visuals from advance strike group!
So, this is the notorious Terron ship.
Surely the gods have sent them to us!
I'll steal that ship's gun that can annihilate Gamilas
and present it to His Great Imperial Majesty!
Victory to Dagum!
Glory to the clan!
Multiple vessels to aft!
Coming out of warp!
Their main force is here, huh?
Their commanding officer is hailing us!
Video transmission!
First contact...
Respond to it.
In the name of His Great Imperial Majesty,
Terron,
I suggest you listen closely.
Language match. Gatlantean.
My name is "Thunderclap" Goran Dagum,
Chief Commander of the Gatlantean Gudaba Expeditionary Force!
I'm Kodai, ship's Tactical Officer.
We have no intent to fight.
We ask that you call off your attack immediately.
Battle is a Warrior's honor.
To withdraw troops is the act of a coward.
There can be no peace.
When your fighters suddenly attacked us,
we were forced to respond in kind.
We are in the middle of a journey.
We don't want any trouble with you.
I laugh!
I order you in the name of His Great Imperial Majesty!
Terrons, surrender to my forces and hand over your ship!
We refuse!
Well said.
If that is your wish...
...I will grant you an honorable death.
They're going to attack!
All hands, go to level 1 battle stations!
We aboard the Kiska struck the first spear against the Yamatte!
We will lift their head high for all to see!
Enemy formation closing in from dead ahead!
Load fore and aft torpedoes.
Shall I launch fighters?
No.
The enemy will attack the instant we deploy our Falcons.
Stand by to drop mines.
Our goal is strictly to defend the ship.
All hands to level 1 battle stations!
I'd prefer to avoid combat.
Damn it, if only we could use the Wave Motion Gun...
Hayashi, report any astronomical bodies
in our immediate vicinity.
Spare any engineers who could serve the empire as science slaves.
But kill the warriors.
Even if they are women, do not spare them!
Fighter formation closing in from 1 o'clock!
Destroyers closing in from 6 o'clock!
Distance, 8,000!
Count, 7!
Ready to engage!
Wait!
Off our 3 o'clock!
A free-floating planet!
Make for the planet!
Hard to starboard!
We're running?
We are.
Fighter formation wiped out!
Enemy vessels closing in!
Ventral hull hit!
Damage control!
Open fire!
Destroyer eliminated.
Hayashi, forward the planet's data for analysis.
Sending data to Operations Officer.
Data received.
Trailing ships closing in!
Raise Wave Motion Barrier!
Turn us around!
Firestorm Direct Strike Gun! Prepare to fire!
Fleeing to that planet, eh?
It won't help.
Firestorm Direct Strike Gun! Prepare to fire!
Activating energy dampers!
Inputting relative impact coordinates!
Pressure climbing in firing chamber!
Open energy transport jump conduits!
Lock on target!
Gliade has struck out too far ahead!
Damn that Gliade... Always in a rush for glory.
Chief Commander,
if we wait, it will throw off the transport coordinates.
Then we don't.
Bear witness to the light of Gatlantis!
Firestorm Direct Strike Gun, fire!
What is that?!
Barrier deflection rate falling!
Damage to hull plating!
That wasn't a direct hit!
It only grazed us?
Radar, pinpoint firing location!
Unable to calculate trajectory!
It must have appeared out of nowhere.
It would seem that the enemy can attack
from outside our own firing range.
Commander...
Advance ship Gliade destroyed!
Terron ship... intact!
They won't die, eh?
Still, that makes that ship all the more worthy
to present to His Majesty!
Main enemy force closing in!
Analysis complete.
The planet possesses a complicated cavity structure.
Understood.
If we stay out here, we'll be a sitting duck.
Commander.
It's the right call.
We're going down to the planet!
Terron ship descending to the planet!
Target their propulsion and force them to make a soft landing!
We will then attack with troops and take the ship!
Vanguard ships, force them down!
Enemy ships overhead!
Start firing SAMs!
Fire!
Multiple unknown targets have appeared to aft!
They are not ships!
Still increasing in number!
Unknown targets have latched on!
Life signs detected in unknown objects.
Tendrils entering through hull breaches.
Commander?
What the‒?!
Wave Motion Barrier output falling!
Barrier collapsing!
Main engine output falling!
If this keeps up, we're dead in the water!
Unknown targets have latched onto enemy ship!
A space life form with the ability to absorb energy...
Kodai, if we don't do something, the ship will‒
Roll the ship! Roll us and shake them off!
Roger!
They're not budging!
Wave motion energy drain, 80%!
We'll be dead in the water in minutes!
All hands, prepare to go to warp!
I think we should warp immediately.
That's crazy!
If we stay here, we're dead in the water!
If we leave the planet,
we'll be a sitting duck for that weapon again.
We should do it!
Since they are an unknown life form,
the dimensional resonance of a warp might dislodge them.
Commander!
Kodai is right.
We have to roll the dice.
Keep her spinning!
Don't let her go out!
Burn out the parts if you have to!
Keep her spinning at full power!
Energy threshold needed for warp in 10 seconds!
Five seconds!
Warp!
Gravity interference waves detected on planet!
Terron ship appears to have performed spatial jump!
I'm seething with rage!
Hey...
Is everyone all right?
Where in the world are we?
What kind of crazy space is this?!
Calm down.
Warning. Mainframe is being tampered with by outside force.
The helm isn't‒ The ship's moving by itself!
Situation report! Are there any ships in the area?
Ch-Checking!
Nothing on radar!
There's nothing on my screen!
Determine current position!
N-No stars are observable!
It's true... Not a single one!
The Yamato appears to have wandered
into some sort of void space
that is cut off from our own universe.
Helm not responding.
Autopilot will not disengage.
Power down engines.
Power down engines!
Power down!
We can't!
We're trying, but she's not doing a thing we say!
Where the heck are we headed?
Sanada, we've been in a situation like this before.
If we assume it's the same as before...
Hey!
Look at that!
...it would most likely make that world our destination.
Nothing ventured, and all that...
Planetary surface confirmed.
Current altitude, 4,200.
The planet's surface is composed of some liquid.
Speed has fallen.
Radar return! Massive floating object dead ahead!
This would appear to be the end of the line.
An enclosed void space, eh?
That is just a theory.
By all rights, a space such as this should not exist.
It is impossible, and yet...
And yet, here we are inside it.
This structure floating above the planet is clearly artificial in origin.
Add to that the loss of control of the ship,
we may assume that some conscious mind has brought us here.
If I may offer an opinion?
Oh, crap! Oh, crap!
You're late!
I'm sorry!
You're our driver, Sawamura?
I'll be right‒
Oh, come on!
I'll get you there safe and sound.
Hey, you should be more careful.
I'm sorry, I‒
Get your hands off me!
What's that opening up there?
Rotate left! Lower boom! Extend boom!
Oh, I get it.
They're sending that out, huh?
We had something like that aboard?
The Ki-8 prototype space boat.
AKA "Stork."
It's an unlisted reserve aircraft.
It's a special-purpose planetary recon boat.
You mean it's‒
Yep, that's what it was for.
Oh, so basically,
you were planning to use this
once you'd pulled off your mutiny.
Sawamura.
Don't be rude!
No, I just meant‒
Sorry about that, ma'am.
That's all right.
After all, it's the truth.
Depth, 50. 55...
60.
Singing?
This is the Yamato.
Stork, what's the matter?
Report your status!
Aihara!
Communications with the Stork have been cut off.
Commander!
Something strange is happening to the planet's surface!
What's that?
It's like a world straight out of myth...
I almost feel like God is toying with us.
Tactical Officer!
Receiving Gamilan mayday!
Nitrogen, 78.1%.
Atmospheric pressure, 1018 hectopascals.
Atmospheric composition and climate closely resemble
that of a tropical rainforest on Earth.
No toxic substances detected.
We'll continue on foot from here.
Are you serious?
-50 decibels... Got it.
Oh, come on... It's crazy to take a Gammie SOS seriously!
Is there even any point to this?
Of course there is.
It was because we believed that other SOS
that we found my brother's Yukikaze on Enceladus.
Watch your step.
Th-Thank you.
What's the holdup?
I knew it...
I've been here before.
I've been here before!
When I was little, I went with my mother
when she was doing field research.
We were in the Amazon!
This place looks exactly like what I saw there.
Don't all jungles look the same?
Of course they don't!
Tactical Officer!
What is it?
Um, I located what seems to be the signal's source...
But, well...
Take a look!
It looks just like it.
It looks just like that sunken battleship
the Yamato was camouflaged as.
Total length, 263 meters.
Basic displacement, 64,000 tons.
Six 46cm guns mounted forward.
Three mounted aft.
The largest surface vessel put to sea during the Pacific War.
The Yamato, first ship of the Yamato class.
This is the Yamato...
What's that supposed to mean?!
How could that ship be here?!
What in the world is going on?!
A place where the impossible becomes reality.
It means that this is that sort of place.
This structure covers the entire surface of the planet!
It would appear that we and the landing party
have been physically separated.
Kodai...
This looks like a way in!
What the‒? What's going on?
From what I can see, this seems like a hotel.
Information Officer, the SOS has disappeared.
This is the right place, though.
What's going on? How is this happening?
I've been to this place, too.
You know this place?
The Hotel Yamato.
Come again?
During the Pacific War, that's what it was called.
Like I care about that!
The numbers go up to 11.
It certainly doesn't seem that tall.
Man, I can't deal with this... This is nuts.
In any case‒
Tactical Officer! The door, it's‒
This is the landing party!
Stork, come in!
I repeat, Stork, come in!
What the hell is going on?!
Pull it together, Sawamura!
What's going on, Analyzer?
Come in, Analyzer!
It's no use. There's no response.
I thought somebody might come.
Of all the stupid... Don't do that!
A Piano?
It's this way.
Hey, wait! Don't leave me!
Tactical Officer!
Hey.
Melch, we've got guests!
Looks like your hard work paid off.
Here I thought we were rescued,
but it's just a bunch of Saltzians...
You sent the mayday?
Yeah.
"Saltzians"?
As I recall, it's a planetary state that was annexed by Gamilas.
They seem to understand what we're saying.
I hadn't heard anything about a Saltzian unit
being deployed in this area.
It's news to me, too.
What unit are you with?
You were asked to identify your unit!
Answer the question, Saltzians!
My gun!
What're you‒
What are you wearing?
What the‒?
What's the matter?
I'm not surprised by anything here anymore.
So uncool.
Look who's talking! What's up with that?
This is my favorite outfit!
If you can't tell us, you can't tell us.
Major!
It was a top-secret mission, right?
Yes. We're not even allowed to discuss what unit we belong to.
I once knew some Saltzians like you people.
I don't have a problem with sticklers like you.
I'm Berger.
Fomt Berger.
I'm Susumu Kodai.
Kodai, huh?
Nice to meet you.
We came to offer assistance, but the door vanished.
The same thing happened to us.
What do you mean?
We can't leave the hotel.
We've tried everything we could think of,
but we're still stuck here.
Sorry we got you stuck in here with us.
You're kidding! There has to be a way out of this place!
Go see for yourself, then.
Fine! I will!
There's no shortage of rooms.
This is amazing! It's so fancy!
There's even a book set out.
This takes me back!
This is a children's book I read as a little girl.
The Helen‒
The Miracle Worker
You read... this?
Yes.
It's a story about a lonely witch.
Once upon a time,
there was a large, blue land that lay far to the west.
One day, a little girl arrived at the blue land.
She had come to the blue land because she wanted human friends.
But no one in the blue land would be her friend.
She grew sad and cried out,
"Why will no one be my friend?"
The people of the blue land hated the little girl.
They despise the strange power that the little girl has.
Strange power?
She could read people's minds.
She's what's called a telepath.
Because of that power, she can see what people are actually feeling.
When she innocently tells others what she has seen,
the people become overwhelmed with suspicions,
begin to hate each other,
and eventually, they begin to fight.
The little girl, now a misanthrope, locks herself away in her home,
but the people who had come to fear her power
call her a witch and try to kill her.
What happened to the girl?
She sets out to find a faraway land
in a ship that God left for her out of pity.
To the land of tomorrow,
which lies just beyond our sight.
It's just a fairy tale.
The Helen Keller
Story
The Miracle Worker
Is that how you blow off steam?
Pretty much.
Anyway, quite the resemblance, huh?
What is?
What resembles what?
Bosun, how much longer will repairs take?
We're double-timing it!
Check back in three hours!
The day after we found ourselves trapped in the hotel,
we began a strange communal life here.
What we've learned
is that this hotel has four floors.
But the indicator on the elevator goes up to 11.
And that elevator seems to be broken because it won't move.
Ultimately, we never found an exit leading to the roof.
The hotel's walls are tough.
We've tried to smash them, but can't make a dent.
We've tried everything that we could think of.
Damn it!
But nothing has worked.
Crap!
The only thing that seemed to offer some hope
Sawamura's hole
was the hole that that dummy Sawamura fell into.
Maybe we're just deluding ourselves, but for now,
digging this hole is our only way to make progress.
Strangely, we're being supplied with just water from somewhere.
If all this is deliberate on the part of the beings who created this world.
What do they intend to do with us?
Our emergency provisions will run out soon.
We're okay for now and are sharing them with the Gamilans,
but unless something changes, it won't be long before...
Hunger awakens conflict.
Who's there?
That was...
Hunger... awakens... conflict?
The voice said, "hunger awakens conflict".
In an alien language?
It was definitely speaking Jirellan.
Lt. Niimi said I was probably imagining things.
But when people are hungry, that's definitely what happens.
Eat up.
I can't! Isn't that your last one?
Don't worry about me, I'm a guy.
Go on.
Thanks.
Look... If you say you heard it, you heard it.
You believe me?
Yeah.
Maybe this crazy world is constructed from your memories.
You knew about the jungle and the battleship, right?
And you also said that you'd been to this hotel before, right?
Yeah.
That just leaves the Jirellan voice you heard...
Yeah...
I've got it!
The Jirellan voice
is the ghost of a woman who was murdered in this hotel!
Are you an idiot?
That's an amusing way of looking at it.
The Jirellans are an extinct race.
So in that sense, maybe they are something like ghosts.
They think we're someone else for now,
but if they ever learn that we're Yamato crew members...
We'll worry about that if the time comes.
It's possible for us to reach a mutual understanding with aliens.
That's what your brother said in his message.
Yes.
We can do it. It'll be okay.
Sheesh!
"Helen Keller was blind and deaf.
When she touched the water,
she understood the relation between..."
Days Spent at the Hotel Yamato
Tomorrow will mark one week...
Meria...
Enemy attack has set off a chain reaction in Block 5's energy tanks!
Evacuate immediately! Now sealing off Block 5!
Meria!
Are you all right?
What is it?
You were moaning, so I got worried.
I'm fine. It's nothing you need to worry about.
Good night.
It's not working, just give up!
We'll never get out no matter how much we dig!
It's just busywork!
If you want to do it, you Saltzians can do it yourselves!
I've had enough of‒
Nobody's giving up!
Gamilan soldiers do what needs to be done
because they have faith in possibility.
We don't give up until the bitter end.
I have nothing but respect for you, Major.
But I can't stand to be around these people any longer!
Sorry about that. He gets that way when he's hungry.
Don't give up until the bitter end, huh?
Oh, it's something somebody once told me.
A superior officer I respected.
I think our own captain said something like that once.
"Don't give up to the bitter end!"
Sounds like a scary old man.
He's an amazing person, though.
I'd like to meet him.
And I'd like to meet your superior officer, too.
Well, then...
I guess I'll go drag Melch back here by the scruff of his neck.
Damn it, damn it!
What a bunch of crap!
Don't overexert yourself.
You're hungry, aren't you?
Long ago
he had a sweetheart named Meria.
Unlike now, he was a upright, respectful young man back then.
I'm having trouble picturing that.
Those three were always together.
Him, Meria, and Neredia.
But after Meria died, he changed.
She died right in front of him, and he couldn't save her.
Meria Rikke
He's always dragging that around with him.
And on top of that, he lost his comrades
and Gen. Domel, a man he looked up to,
in battle against the Yamato.
The only thing that keeps Berger going now
is his thirst for revenge against the Yamato.
The Yamato...
Who was that "Meria" you mentioned last night?
Meria is Neredia's little sister.
She was her little sister.
"Was"?
Do you have any siblings?
No, I don't.
I have someone who's like a big brother,
I guess. He has a scar just like yours.
I'm flattered.
Major...
"Fomt" is fine.
Fomt, what sort of race were the Jirellans?
They're witches.
Witches?
It's a story about a lonely witch.
They read people's minds.
They're like monsters out of stories.
The people who had come to fear her power
call her a witch and try to kill her.
The Jirellans all died out, didn't they?
Yeah. Oh, there were two on Gamilas.
But they were the only survivors.
But Neredia said that there weren't any Jirellans left anywhere.
If there's just two women, the race is as good as extinct.
I'll clean it up.
Sorry about that.
Don't mention it.
Video message from the homeworld!
First Minister Sabera!
Report, mighty Thunderclap.
We still have no firm leads.
However, I have another prize.
His Majesty is sure to be pleased.
Simpleton!
His Majesty desires the prize he ordered you to claim!
The World of Tranquility!
Press on with the capture of the secret Aquarian techniques
that are hidden there, their cloaking technology!
The empire desires technology to uphold
its national polity and establish hegemony.
Should you fail to locate the World of Tranquility,
make amends with your death.
Yes, Minister.
I await the good news.
Stupid little girl...
Chief Commander!
We've located traces of a spatial jump!
Good! We will now pursue the Terron ship!
But the First Minister said to‒
I don't care what she said!
All ships, take up positions for spatial jump!
"Helen Keller was blind and deaf.
All she had
was the sense of touch."
This is Jirellan writing!
"Eyes reflect darkness,
and ears hear silence.
Those who take the darkness to be reality
and are swallowed up by the silence,
will destroy themselves through their mutual distrust.
Those who attain the 11th level
will see the world for what it truly is."
The 11th level?!
Does it mean this?
Come here, everyone!
What's wrong?
You came here to steal this, didn't you?!
In ancient times, the World of Tranquility
is said to have shone in a dull gray sky.
The hand of Heaven must be at work!
Because we pursued the Terron ship,
we have found the treasure world!
This is my glory!
I won't surrender it to that little girl!
Identifying vessels that have appeared in orbit!
Gatlantean!
It's those damn barbarians...
Wait!
No way! There wasn't a stairway here before!
These people are the enemy. This food is ours alone.
That's right!
This belongs to us!
What the‒?
This must be the bridge.
Any sign of them?
Sawamura!
Stay back!
This food is ours!
There's none for you Saltzians!
Melch! Stop acting stupid!
What're you saying, Major?!
We can't trust these people!
That isn't food!
Shut up!
How did he get a gun?
I don't know.
Come now, you have them, too.
That's enough, Melch!
You have to come to your senses, Major!
Saltzians can't be trusted!
Cut it out!
We can't coexist with Terrons!
Terrons?
We've been deceived all this time.
These people aren't Saltzians.
The man standing next to you is a member of the Yamato's crew.
Come on, that's crazy. Right?
I don't believe it...
You're one of them?!
What's the matter? Shoot.
Why don't you shoot?
Berger, we fought against Gen. Domel.
He worried about his men to the very end.
He remained true to his principles.
Did you hear that?
He killed him!
Your comrades! Gen. Domel!
These people killed them!
They're your sworn enemy!
Even if
we were born on different worlds,
we can understand each other.
That's awfully idealistic.
It's something my brother left in a message before he died.
Shoot him, Berger!
Shoot him!
I think it's time...
...we ended this little farce!
Deep down, I always suspected.
That you were behind all this.
How did you know?
You didn't react at all when you saw Kiryu.
Even though she's the spitting image of your own sister.
Plus,
the real Neredia calls me Fomt.
I didn't probe your memories well enough, I see.
Uninvited guests have arrived.
What happened?
Kodai! I got through to the Stork!
What in the world?!
Damn it... These men were Gatlantean!
Did you lure them here?
Like you did with us?
They came here in search of this world's power.
But in the end, they were driven by their mistrust to destroy one another.
And the same should have happened to you.
This world is sacred ground to us Jirellans.
Our progenitor, Shambleau of Aquarius.
I knew it! A Jirellan!
Why go to all this trouble?
Where's Neredia?
She was never here.
What?
She is outside this world.
She never came to the hotel.
You manipulated his memories.
Just like on the Yamato that time.
That was the doing of two who had gone over to Gamilas' cause.
Then who are you people?
When our homeworld fell,
the handful of pilgrims who were here escaped its destruction.
Oh, I get it...
"By the wall, I will say a word to you.
Take my word.
Give ear to my instructions."
It meant this?
Kiryu!
"Seeds were sown across the galaxies.
Seven days after those seeds, the many races, gather here,
make your hearts one.
Enter the ring of light
and join hands,
you brothers of the galaxies who all share the genes of Aquarius.
Do so, and the seal will be broken.
Odyssey of the Celestial Ark...
...awaken from your long slumber."
You, too.
Leaving our place of refuge and setting out again...
We cannot do that.
Even if you lock yourselves away in here,
you're only waiting for extinction.
Believe in tomorrow.
So will we.
Do we... have a tomorrow?
What's your name?
Loerelai Loer.
What's‒
"Our origin."
"Time is cyclical."
"Setting out."
"Preserving the species."
"Rejuvenation."
"Birth."
"Humanoid shape..."
What's happening?
Your ride is here!
Analyzer!
Burn it to ash!
Smoke them out!
Thrash those who would defy the empire!
Now is our chance to seize the treasure world!
Hull repairs complete!
The planetary surface appears to be crumbling!
Yamato, do you copy?
Stork here!
Now returning to the Yamato!
Survey team's launch is aboard!
He's always making me worry...
That idiot.
The launch is leaving the Lambeer!
What's going on?
Beginning approach.
This is the Mirangal.
You are cleared to land.
Kodai!
We'll file a report later.
What's our situation?
The enemy has set up a blockade in orbit.
It's probably just a matter of time
before they launch an all-out offensive.
Commander, would you give me command
for the duration of the battle?
What?
We have a shot at victory.
I have an idea for how to counter
the enemy's out-of-range attack.
On my authority as first officer,
I hereby transfer command to the Tactical Officer.
Kodai.
From here on out, you are in command of the ship.
Sir!
We intend to hold them off and make sure
the old-timers and kids make it home!
If the rest of you are Gamilan men, you should understand this!
Give me your trust
and follow me!
Zar belk!
Garle Gamilon! Garle Gamilon!
Objects surfacing off our 9 o'clock!
Gamilan ships!
Gamilan fleet is pulling alongside the Yamato.
Stand by to attack!
Hold your fire.
They're on our side.
Hang on, when you said we had a shot...
That's right.
We aren't alone.
Attention, all hands.
The Yamato will now engage the enemy
in tandem with the Gamilan fleet
and destroy them!
Launch all fighter squadron aircraft.
Commence joint operation with Gamilan fighters.
I repeat, launch all fighter squadron aircraft.
This is 104, Sawamura!
Launching!
Klim Melch, launching!
Alpha 2, Yamamoto!
Launching!
The combined air wing will intercept
the carriers closing in from our right flank.
The Yamato and the Berger fleet will halt
the advance of the main enemy force!
All hands to battle formation!
Deploy battle deck!
There's that attack...
It's not a problem.
We detected a spatial wave motion echo in the enemy's attack
that's identical to what we saw in the Rainbow Cluster battle.
It's only 73% accurate, but we can predict the emergence coordinates.
Where did that come from?!
That was...
Nirvales destroyed!
Unable to compute trajectory!
...a transport system?
This is the Yamato.
Transmitting enemy prediction data.
Link all your ships to counter their attack.
Incoming!
Bearing, 33! VS4!
Yes! It works!
Why does it not hit them?!
Chief Commander!
The planet! It's‒
Commander! Look at that!
Unusual phenomena detected around planet!
Structure closing in from above!
This is this world's true form...
The planet...
Chief Commander.
There is an emergency message from the First Minister.
To what do I owe‒
Is it true that you have located the world?
It is!
Halt your attack at once.
How unusual.
I am moments from destroying the Terron Yamatte
and those blue Gamilan vermin‒
You fool!
How dare you damage the world I mean to present to His Majesty?!
Imbecile!
As one would expect from the former head of a gang of brigands.
You were not worthy to wield the Firestorm Direct Strike Gun
that our Gamilan science slaves constructed.
Shut your mouth!
Enemy fleet now in firing range!
Even without the Wave Motion Gun...
The Yamato can do this.
Enemy fleet closing in further!
Have the Kiska squadron form up and attack from their flank!
As for us, we will take the Yamatte's head!
Slay the enemy!
We'll crown ourselves with glory!
Open fire!
Target enemy flagship!
Ranging complete!
Targeting complete!
Fire!
Kiska here, we are about to enter combat airspace.
You're going down!
We're under attack!
They must have approached using the rings' ice for cover.
Such insolence...
Anti-air combat!
Sawamura, let's finish off that cruiser!
Nemoto!
My hand slipped.
Yamatte closing in!
Heavy damage to energy transfer conduits!
Firestorm Direct Strike Gun offline!
Damn them...
Point the bow towards the planet!
We'll seize the core of the planet ourselves!
Enemy flagship has deserted the battle line.
New course, descent trajectory towards planet.
What's going on?! Requesting orders! Requesting orders!
Megaruda has deserted the battle line!
Friendlies are requesting instructions!
Capt. Parakas?
Dagum!
And you call yourself a warrior?!
Major! The Lambeer has run aground!
They're stuck in the planet's surface and are unable to move!
Lambeer stranding point is along the enemy flagship's course!
I-It's what?!
Don't give up!
Try using the gravity balancers!
Y-Yes, sir!
Enemy ship detected in orbit!
Kodai!
The Lambeer's run aground on the surface.
Let us handle these guys!
Go rescue them with the Yamato!
You only have a handful of ships!
Can you handle them, Berger?
Hey, I'm giving you a plum role here.
Just shut up and do me this favor, okay?
Don't worry about us.
We'll get out of this on our own.
Would you do as I say for once?
Fomt...
Down there...
I ran into Meria.
What are you talking about?
When we get back home, I'll tell you all about it.
Be seeing you.
That fool...
We're changing course!
Hard to port!
We will now pursue the enemy flagship!
We've cleared their air patrol!
They're all yours!
There is no longer any honor in this battle.
Inform all ships!
Enemy fighter overhead!
Melch, you're too far ahead!
Got him...
Melch... Are you kidding me?!
A death like this... I'm okay with.
Sorry, Neredi. I don't think I'll be making it home.
Yamazaki, can you give me 100% in this situation?
If I cut the power going to the Wave Motion Barrier and main guns
and patch in the auxiliaries, it should work. No, it will work!
Then do it!
Gamilan ship dead ahead!
What a nuisance!
Butcher them!
Yamatte closing in at high speed!
I laugh!
Use Type-3's!
Roger!
I'll turn the tables on them!
The Megaruda has no blind spots!
Obliterate them!
Shima!
I've got this!
Stand by to fire rocket anchor!
Target their starboard stern!
R-Roger!
Ready to drop anchor
Ready to fire!
Drop anchor!
Fire!
What was that?
Reel in the anchor!
Close-quarters combat!
I won't lose!
The Megaruda will never lose!
All stations, prepare for combat!
Smash them!
Fire!
Glory to‒
Enemy ship seems to have exploded!
We're free of the obstruction!
They did it?
What's the Yamato's status?
What about Fomt?
Meria, I tried to join you but failed again...
The week we spent on that world in that hotel
was apparently just half a day to the Yamato.
This world is a relic of the ancient Aquarius civilization.
The Jirellan's holy land, hidden away in the dull gray skies,
as well as a space ark that travels the galaxies.
I wonder if all our races really can trace
their origins back to the same source...
Did the Aquarians believe that the seeds they had sown
would eventually sprout not into conflict, but rather trust?
No one will ever know.
Hey, look!
It's vanishing!
Sanada?
To be able to cloak a mass of that scale...
This is science beyond our comprehension.
Finally, the ark set out into the sea of stars.
Having lost their home, the Jirellans
might be cosmic vagabonds forever.
But it's the same thing as us that allows
them to continue on their voyage.
A hope for tomorrow.
Farewell, farewell, my friend.
What's that?
This is a brief goodbye for now.
Farewell, farewell, my friend.
Let's meet again one day somewhere out here in these skies.
Though our bodies may go their separate ways,
This is a pretty good farewell, too.
Our hearts will remain as one.
All ahead half!
Set sail for Earth!
Our journey is not yet over.
To give hope to our homeland, the ship travels on.
Fires resulting from riots
have broken out in sectors 8 and 21!
Riot suppression has resulted
in heavy casualties
to both civilians and security forces.
Contaminated area spreading!
Sealing off through level 17.
Issuing mandatory evacuation order.
It's been 324 days since the Yamato left Earth.
The one-year time limit will be up in just 41 days...
We are out of time.
Will the Yamato really‒
Hey, hold it!
Hijikata!
Where are you going?
And you are?
Hajime Saito, formerly of the 7th Cosmo Marine Regiment!
He has something to say to me.
Let's hear it.
If I may speak freely, we're putting down riots day after day!
I've had it up to here with pointing my gun at civilians!
Cosmo Marine guns aren't meant to be turned on fellow humans!
How long is this hell going to go on?
My best friend told me that he would return, no matter what.
And he will!
Cdr. Hijikata!
We're picking up a hyperspace message
from outside the solar system!
Video transmission!
It's... It's the Yamato!